*music*
Well, good morning, church. Good to see you again.
So glad that you have joined us as we continue this series through the book of Ruth.
We started two weeks ago with an overview of how the book works, and spoiler alert, I read the end.
So you already know where we're headed.
But we're gonna try and sit in the tension as we work our way through back to the ending that we already know is coming.
We started with an overview of how the book works.
It is a story, a literal story about individuals who went through tremendous suffering and yet saw God's redemption in their life.
But it's also a story about God's plan of redemption for the whole world.
It starts with the overwhelming suffering of one family and ends with the line of Jesus who brings about the redemption for all of creation.
I quoted one pastor who said the book of Ruth is the story of the whole Bible told in four chapters through three characters.
It's a story of God working out what seems to us to be a painstakingly slow process of redemption.
But remember we said that it might seem slow to us, but it's not slow to God, that God is patient, inviting all of his creation to seek comfort in his arms, to seek redemption through his process.
So it seems slow to us, but it's God's grace.
It's his generosity that makes his redemption so slow because he's wanting and waiting for more people to find comfort in his grace.
Last week, Kent did an excellent job of helping us understand culturally the level of suffering that Ruth and Naomi were experiencing.
They faced physical, emotional, spiritual, psychological suffering.
All of the suffering that any of us will face throughout our lives, they suffered all of it.
And he focused on how turning away from the things of this world, Ruth, turning her back to Moab, turning her back to her false gods, her false idols, the things that the world told her would find comfort and peace, and turning towards the God of the Old Testament, turning towards Yahweh.
It was like a seed planted in the ashes awaiting the redemption that God will ultimately have.
We intentionally chose the book of Ruth for the season of Lent because Lent is all about acknowledging, encountering, and voluntarily experiencing the suffering of this broken world.
As we look with anticipation towards the redemption that is fulfilled and secured on Easter.
We have the expressed privilege of living in a place where there are all four seasons, right?
And our whole city shuts down for a week called Apple Blossom.
You guys know this.
I avoid the city at all costs during that week.
I know many of you love to participate.
But it is this, it's this annual reminder that when a seed is planted in the ground and dies, it ultimately brings forth life.
And isn't that a picture of our spiritual lives?
If we're willing to lay our life down before the hands of the ultimate good father.
And if we're willing to die to ourselves, to be planted in the ashes, that ultimately he will bring about his redemption and restoration.
So I hope throughout this series that we continue to sit in the suffering of our three main characters.
And that we begin to see God's slow working redemption plans in their lives.
I hope that it builds anticipation for us as we prepare to celebrate on Easter Sunday.
Now, I do have some good news.
I think Kent used the word suffering about 60 times last week.
Does that sound right?
I have some good news.
We're still going to sit in suffering.
But today, we will slowly begin to see some good news.
Some seeds of redemption in the midst of suffering.
You guys, does that sound like a plan?
All right.
Let's pray and we'll get started.
Father in heaven, you are good.
You are patient.
You are kind.
You are compassionate and gracious, slow to anger, abounding in steadfast love.
God, may we, as we sit in the story of Ruth and Naomi and Boaz this morning, may we have eyes to see all of the ways that you are bringing about redemption in the midst of our own self.
May we see that you are a God that is good and that can be trusted with our lives.
That if we would have the boldness of faith to lay down our life before you, that you will resurrect it in your life.
God, give us eyes to see, ears to hear.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
I grew up in one of those churches where we went to church three times on Sunday and once on Wednesday.
Anybody else?
Yeah, that's right.
I loved my church.
I enjoyed the experience that I had.
Everything except the preaching, really, was where I struggled as a kid.
I remember always trying to come up with creative ideas to avoid sitting through the sermon.
I could still take you to my little Baptist church in Inwood, West Virginia right now and show you the best places to hide if you didn't want to be found.
I have, for the sake of the parents that have children there, I have not gone and taught a seminar for how to avoid sermons.
But I know the irony, right, the irony that I am now up here preaching today.
However, once in a while, we would have these services called testimony services.
And for me, I was like, all right, I can get behind this, right?
The boring preacher is going to sit down for the Sunday and the real people with the real lives, they're going to come up and they're going to talk about God's faithfulness in their lives.
I remember getting excited for those days because stories are powerful.
They have a unique way of shaping us.
They grasp our imagination in ways that a sermon never could.
In them, we are often able to see our own stories with fresh eyes.
We can see the ways that God might be working in our lives that we don't currently have eyes to see.
We're inspired to believe that maybe, just maybe, God might be able to use us far more than we actually ever imagined before.
And it's my opinion, and this might not be everyone's opinion, it's my opinion.
The only thing better than a personal testimony is a biographical testimony.
A testimony composed by a person who has mastered the art of storytelling.
They can take this powerful story of redemption in God's life and they can tell it in a way that gets even more into our soul.
They often have a way of narrating the story that makes us feel like we're in the room where it happened.
I'm looking for my Hamilton fans.
Anybody?
In the room where it happened.
All right, cool.
Moving on.
Nobody got that joke.
All right, you guys need to get better taste in movies, musicals.
Let's do this.
All right.
They often make us feel like we're in the room where it happened.
They have, thank you.
They have a way of narrating the story.
They draw out connections and foreshadow future scenes, crescendoing to the resolution in a way that we will never forget.
And this is what the book of Ruth is.
It's a biographical testimony narrated by an author who hasn't just mastered the art of storytelling, but they have been inspired by the Holy Spirit to write the very words of Scripture that God wanted preserved for us.
The reality is I know most of you will likely not remember anything I have to say, any of my main points for any length of time.
But I believe if you can get the story of Ruth's life in your heart and in your imagination, it can carry you through tremendous periods of suffering in your own life.
So my plan for today, I wish that I worked hard to try and find a creative outline with a main point and all the fun stuff that I like to do.
I just couldn't do it.
So the plan for today is we're just going to read chapter, we're just going to read chapter two verse by verse.
I'm going to try and do my best to help you see what the author is doing with Ruth's very powerful testimony.
And hopefully through the story of Ruth, we can see our own stories with fresh eyes.
And we can see ways that God might be working in our lives that we haven't been previously aware of.
And maybe, just maybe, we can be inspired to believe that God might be able to use us in ways that we've never even imagined before.
Sound like a plan?
I don't know why I ask you guys that.
I do it every time.
All right, one, chapter one, starting in verse 22, and then we'll do most of chapter two this morning.
Remember, where Kent left off, Ruth and Naomi are in an utterly helpless situation.
They are childless widows with no household identity in a patriarchal culture.
They are just barely surviving with probably, if they were to put odds on them surviving this suffering,
they would probably put it in the lower 10%.
They are just trying to hang on.
With no realistic hope to get out of the situation.
They don't have any plans for how they're going to get out.
All they're trying to do is survive today.
This is the first glimpse of redemption that we have in the story, filled with suffering.
It just so happened that Ruth and Naomi happened to be coming home just at the time the barley harvest was coming.
They arrived at harvest time when food would be plentiful for the first time in a long time.
The famine has come to an end.
And not only has the famine come to an end, but they are arriving at harvest time.
And with the gleaning laws of the Old Testament that we're going to get into in a minute,
this would give these vulnerable widows a glimmer of hope that they might just possibly have the meal that they've been longing for,
that they're desperate for, that they're in need of.
It just so happened that they arrived at the time of the barley harvest.
I want to point out that we talked about Ruth and Naomi being widows.
But not only is Ruth a widow, she's also a foreigner and an orphan.
Kent talked last week about the importance of Ruth going back to her home
so that she could face the suffering with her real mother,
the one who would help her in her grieving process.
But she gave all of that away to follow Yahweh.
And so now Ruth is not just a widow, but she's a foreigner and an orphan.
She is a real person, but she also functions as a literary device
for the entire group of vulnerable people in the Old Testament.
She is a widow, a foreigner, and an orphan.
And the story of Ruth, the testimony of Ruth,
gives us God's heart for the widow, the orphan, and the foreigner,
the most vulnerable people among us.
Chapter 2, verse 1.
Now, this is weird.
It has nothing to do with the story, seemingly, right?
Now, Naomi had a relative on her husband's side,
a man of standing from the clan of Elimelech, whose name was Boaz.
You guys ever watched a movie where they get you bought into the story of some individuals,
and then the scene cuts, and you're in a scene with a new character
that you haven't met before and seemingly has nothing to do with the characters
that the story writer got you invested in?
Thank you.
I appreciate that.
I have as well.
We're on the same page.
That's what the author of Ruth is doing here.
She's introducing a new character that to the original hearers,
as they're hearing the story, this has nothing to do with the story they've got invested in,
but they're quickly going to, their paths are quickly going to cross.
And these stories are going to be interwoven together.
Naomi has a relative who's wealthy and of high social status and character in the town of Bethlehem.
Verse 2.
And Ruth, the Moabite, said to Naomi,
let me go to the fields and pick up the leftover grain behind anyone whose eyes I find favor.
Now Naomi said to her, go ahead, my daughter.
So she went out and entered a field and began to glean behind the harvesters.
Ruth here shows an incredible amount of knowledge in the law of God that likely came from her living in Naomi's household for 10 years.
She wastes no time.
She knows that the Old Testament has laws of gleaning where widows can go into the fields behind the harvesters and glean and pick up the leftovers.
The Old Testament law, and let me see, I wrote it down so that I didn't forget it.
My notes are so small.
There it is.
Leviticus 19, Leviticus 23, and Deuteronomy 24 all dictate that the Israelite landowners are required by law not to harvest the edges of their fields
and not to go back through the fields a second time.
The edges of the fields, the stalks of the grain dropped by the harvesters, they are all to be left for the widow, the foreigner, and the orphan.
This is a clear reminder to God's people that the land is not theirs.
It is his, and he gave it to them as a gift, and they are to steward it as if it is his and not theirs.
That he cares for all of creation, that he cares for the most vulnerable, and that his land is to be used to take care of everyone who has need.
And so Naomi and Ruth, they know this, but what's interesting to me is that Naomi's obviously able-bodied.
She just got back from a 50-mile journey from Moab, and yet she doesn't have the heart.
She doesn't have the hope to go out and glean.
She's sitting in the midst of her suffering.
She says, call me Mara.
The Lord has been bitter to me.
She's sitting in her suffering, and Ruth, on behalf of Naomi, says, I'm going to go out and glean for both of us.
I'm going to be aggressive in my gleaning to take care of both me and you, and what I need you to hear is sometimes you're in the midst of suffering so bad that you don't even have the hope to move on,
and what you need is some community around you, somebody that can see a hope for you even when you can't see a hope for yourself.
And so Naomi doesn't have the energy.
She doesn't have the hope.
She doesn't have the belief in God to take care of her, and so she's sitting at home struggling, wrestling with crippling depression, just ready for it to be over, and Ruth says, I've got hope enough for both.
And so when you're in the midst of your suffering, may you surround yourself.
Even if it's somebody that's suffering alongside of you, may you surround yourself with people who can see hope for you, who can believe in hope with you.
Ruth says, I am going to go out, and I'm going to glean.
I'm going to take care of us.
I'm going to rest on the character of God, the character of God that legally demanded God's people.
Even when they didn't have the heart of God inside of them, they still had laws commanding them to take care of the widow, the orphan, and the foreigner.
So Ruth goes out.
She has incredible knowledge of the law.
And what's interesting here is although we don't necessarily see God actively show up in the book of Ruth until the very end,
we don't see him doing anything crazy or miraculous to our eyes.
We see him working through providential moments all throughout the book.
Verse 3, she goes out to glean, and she just happened to enter a field that belonged to Boaz.
Remember our wealthy relative of good standing?
It just, as it turned out, she was working in a field that belonged to Boaz, who was from the clan of Elimele.
And the Hebrew here clearly articulates, as I think the English translation does a really good job of,
as it turned out, is very clearly saying this is not a coincidence.
God is at work in the steps that Ruth is taking.
He is taking her to a place where he can bring about the redemption that she's just barely holding on to hope that she might have.
It's seemingly a coincidental encounter, but ultimately it's God working out his redemption through the kindness of people that are obedient to him.
It's obviously divine providence.
And again, if you are a Hebrew listener of this text for the first time, you're going to hear that phrase,
it happened as it happened, and you're immediately going to think of the first time that that was brought up in the Old Testament.
Now, most of us, because we don't read the text in the original language and because we don't,
our whole lives aren't baked around the story of God like they were in the Old Testament, we don't think like that.
But they would have heard this phrase and they would have immediately thought of the first time it was used in the book of Genesis.
And it was used of Abraham's servant going to find a wife for Isaac.
So there's this thing in biblical interpretation called the law of firsts,
which is when a phrase or a word happens for the first time,
it is often setting up what that word is going to mean throughout the rest of Scripture.
Because remember, Scripture is God's grand narrative.
It is a library of multiple books, but all of these books are one story of God's redemption from beginning to end.
And so they would have heard this and the readers of this would have thought,
okay, this isn't possible.
There's no way that the writer of this book is connecting a Moabite widow
to one of the matriarchs of our nation
who would carry along the line of Israel.
It's almost as if the narrator is saying,
hey, God might be doing far more than you think he's doing in this story.
You might, you have been hearing me tell this story about Ruth
and you might be thinking, oh, God's going to do a great thing.
He's going to redeem this lady's story.
He's going to help her survive.
But no, the author is saying, what if?
What if God is so good that he's not just going to redeem her story,
but he's going to use her to redeem the whole world.
He's going to use her to be a part of the lineage of the nation of Israel.
How audacious of a God do we serve that he takes a Moabite widow
and brings her into the family of God and uses her in an incredible way
to bring about the line of Jesus Christ?
Ruth and Naomi just happen to arrive at the beginning of the barley harvest,
and Ruth just happens to stumble into Boaz Field the first day she goes to glean.
And you can almost hear the narrator telling you God is at work bringing about redemption
in the midst of it.
Verse 4.
Again, we just keep falling into God's redemption plan in the life of Ruth and Naomi.
Not only do they just happen to show up at barley harvest time,
not only does she just happen to show up at Boaz's field,
but he just happens to show up right when she gets there.
This is the third clear evidence of God at work
in seemingly coincidental moments in the story.
Remember, Boaz is a wealthy landowner, a man of status.
He likely has lots of places to be and lots of things to do,
but it just so happens that he shows up to this field when Ruth is there.
Remember week one, I told you the names are highly symbolic in the book of Ruth,
and Boaz's name is no exception to this.
Boaz's name means in him is strength.
And this is the play, this is the character that Boaz is going to play throughout the story,
that he has strength, not in and of himself, but in Yahweh.
That Boaz's strength comes from God.
And the first words out of his mouth demonstrate this.
He greets the harvesters of his field by saying,
the Lord be with you.
Remember, we're set in the scene of Judges,
a time where everybody is turning their back on God
and doing what is right in their own eyes.
And yet, Boaz is a man of character.
Boaz is a man who's remained faithful in the midst of the rebellion of God's people.
And Boaz is reminding the harvesters of his field that this field is not my field.
This field is not your field.
This field is Yahweh's field that has been given to us as a gift.
And we are going to steward it as if that is true.
He greets his workers, reminding them that this is God's land
and God is present with them as they harvest it.
This is a field that would be very friendly to the gleaners.
And Ruth notices it immediately.
And he notices Ruth immediately.
And this is where I think some of you that have heard popular versions
of the book of Ruth being taught,
this is where our modern American familiarity with romantic comedy shows up.
And we just do this thing that Americans do
where we read the Scriptures as if they were written directly to us.
And we put our culture and our storylines on their culture and their storylines.
It's very American of us to do.
I just want to make sure we're aware of it.
And so immediately, because we're so familiar with how romantic comedies work
in our culture, we're like,
Oh, Boaz must be hot and bothered for Ruth, right?
He sees her in the field.
Who's that woman belonged to?
She's got to be good looking, right?
He's got to be interested.
We immediately start going down this road of romance.
But I think that's a bit of a jump.
Boaz, as a man of high standing in the nation of Israel
and how marriage and relationships would work at that time,
would have no interest in Ruth as a Moabite widow,
who's likely still dressed as a mourner showing up in the field.
And that's likely why he recognized her,
because she's still dressed as a widow in mourning.
And he sees a woman who hasn't been in his fields previously dressed as a widow.
His attention towards her is likely more rooted in his generous heart for those in need.
Now, don't worry.
The romance will come.
But I think the romance we will see between Ruth and Boaz goes well beyond physical attraction.
Nothing about Ruth's situation on the surface would make her a good candidate for Boaz.
In our over-sexualized culture, listen to this.
In our over-sexualized culture, I think we need to recapture the beauty of opposite-sex friendships
that aren't charged by lust or selfish intention.
We are brothers and sisters in Christ.
And we allow ourselves to be discipled by the culture that says all male-female relationships
is angling for some type of thing that we can get benefit out of.
And what if we recaptured that and we began to live as if we were a family of God together?
We need each other.
Brothers and sisters need each other.
So I think what's going on here is a little bit deeper than just Boaz's hot and bothered for Ruth.
All right, verse 6 and 7.
We'll keep going.
Oh, we're doing on time.
Great.
Awesome.
The overseer replied,
She is the Moabite who came back from Moab with Naomi.
She said,
Please let me glean and gather among the sheaves behind the harvesters.
She came into the field and has remained here for morning until now,
except for a short time of rest in the shelter.
Boaz's foreman immediately informs him,
probably in like an awkward way of like,
this woman is asking for way more than what the law of Israel requires.
Many scholars have said what Ruth is doing is asking for way more than just gleaning.
She's asking to go out behind the harvester.
She's asking,
she's asking,
she's making a bold request,
a bold proclamation,
a bold prayer for both her survival and for the survival of Naomi.
She's like,
I've got a friend who doesn't have the hope to see God's faithfulness yet,
but I have a friend and I'm going to have hope for me and for her.
I'm going to ask for more than just what the gleaning laws would require.
Many scholars think that she just has no clue what's going on in the nation of Israel,
but I would argue differently.
I think what Ruth shows is she shows an outsider's perspective on the heart of God,
that she's heard stories of the God of Israel in light of the Moabite God.
She's heard about these laws that the God of Israel has imposed to take care of the widow,
the orphan,
and the stranger,
and that she is aware of God's heart for the widow,
the orphan,
and the stranger.
She's asking Boaz to see beyond the letter of the law to the spirit of the law.
This is Sermon on the Mount type stuff.
You have heard it said,
but I say to you.
Ruth wants more than religious obedience.
She's asking for sacrificial love.
If we have any lawyers in the room this morning,
I'm sorry.
I'm going to take one shot and move on.
As is the case with pretty much any written law,
a good enough lawyer can get you out of it if they try hard enough.
And many Jews at the time would do just that.
Many land-owning Jews would obey the very strictest,
most ungenerous,
literal translation of the law.
They would ensure that the harvesters harvested as much as the field as possible,
leaving next to nothing for the gleaners to pick up.
One scholar I read said that gleaning in many Jewish fields
would be the financial equivalent of collecting cans to sell.
If you were lucky,
you would work all day and just get enough for a single meal.
And here's where I want to point out.
Landowners who just obeyed the letter of the law
could likely be elders in their synagogues,
but would be missing the very heart of God.
And I wonder how many people in churches in America today
would fall in this category where if you look at their lives,
man, they're just obedient to the cultural expectations
of what a good Christian looks like.
And they might find themselves in leadership positions
all around churches and doing things in the name of God,
but what if it's just religious obedience
and they haven't really been transformed by the heart of God?
I've got to ask the question here in the room this morning,
how many of us are just cultural Christians,
just doing the things that we're supposed to do,
but we haven't been captured by the generous heart of God
for those in need around them?
Boaz demonstrates that he has begun to grasp the heart of God,
and Ruth has begun to grasp the heart of God,
and she needs more than legalistic obedience to the law of God.
She needs outrageous generosity if she's going to survive and take care of now.
So, Boaz said to Ruth,
my daughter, listen to me.
Do not go and glean in another field.
Don't go away from me.
Stay here with the women who work for me.
Watch the field where the men are harvesting,
and follow along after the women.
I have told the men not to lay a hand on you,
and whenever you are thirsty,
get a drink from the water the men have filled.
Boaz responds with the tremendous generosity
that we would expect of a person
who has experienced the radical grace and mercy of God.
Not only does he permit her request,
but he goes above and beyond,
inviting her to drink fresh water
from the water that his employees have drawn,
promising her safety.
And many scholars think when he says,
watch the fields,
that he's actually offering her continued gleaning rights,
not just in his barley harvest,
but in the wheat harvest and beyond.
He's saying,
you stay with me for as long as you need to stay with me.
You will be taken care of,
and you will be safe.
To read this as Boaz being generous
and hopes to have a physical relationship with Ruth
is to miss his embodiment of the law of God.
Boaz is demonstrating a love of God
and a love of neighbor,
which all of the law is wrapped up in.
All of God's law is not wrapped up
in following it strictly to obedience,
getting a lawyer, getting a pastor,
getting a preacher to tell you
that you can just do this, this, or this.
All of the law is wrapped up in these two commandments.
Love the Lord your God with all of your heart,
soul, mind, and strength,
and love your neighbor as yourself.
Verse 10.
At this, she bowed down with her face to the ground,
and she asked him,
why have I found such favor in your eyes
that you would notice me, listen, a foreigner?
Ruth went into this request
knowing it was a bold request,
likely fearful that she was not only gonna get shot down,
but she was gonna get kicked out of the field altogether.
She was making a bold, bold request,
and Boaz takes her request and doubles down,
and we're gonna see him later even triple down,
and she says, why have you done this?
She's shocked, and she's surprised.
I'm a foreigner.
He wants to know why Boaz is treating her like this,
and he gives us the answer, and guess what?
The answer is not, I saw you in the field,
and you looked kind of hot.
All right, 11 and 12.
His response shows,
she says, why have you seen me?
I'm a foreigner.
And his response shows,
essentially, I think that he's affirming
her conversion into the nation of Israel.
We said that when she turned her back on Moab,
and when she told Naomi,
your God is my God,
that that was her conversion moment.
She's saying, I am going to live,
surrendered to the people of Israel.
And to this point,
it looks like everybody is still treating her
like a Moabite woman,
but Boaz sees the conversion that happened on the road.
He sees that she is now surrendered to Yahweh,
and not only does he give her physical provision,
but he gives her spiritual acceptance into the community.
He essentially affirms her conversion
on the road to Bethlehem,
and welcomes her as a convert into the nation of Israel.
He doesn't just give her physical provision,
but communal fellowship.
And look, he then prays a prayer of blessing over her.
He wants her to experience the provision of Yahweh
that encouraged her to leave everything behind to follow him.
But notice that he doesn't just pray for her
to be blessed by God.
He views himself as an instrument
in the hands of Yahweh's provision.
He doesn't just ask God to bless her,
but he blesses her in the name of God.
This is what it looks like to follow God.
Not just to say,
I hope you get better.
I hope God takes care of you.
I'm praying for you.
No, it's faith in action.
It's prayer and blessing.
This is James 2.
What good is our faith
if we just pray for people and wish them well,
but do nothing actually to help them in their time of need?
And one of the major themes of the book of Ruth,
and a major theme of this message,
is God's redemptive work
often includes the participation of these people.
We are invited to pray,
may your kingdom come
and your will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
And then we are called to participate in that prayer,
cultivating God's kingdom on earth as it is in heaven,
doing his will in our lives and to those around us.
Boaz prays a blessing over Ruth,
but then he becomes a blessing to Ruth.
Verse 13,
may I continue to find favor in your eyes, my Lord,
she said,
you have put me at ease by spreading,
by speaking kindly to your servant,
though I do not have standing as one of your servant.
Ruth perceives the message,
receives the message with overwhelming gratitude.
This doesn't take away any of her previous sufferings,
but it's a glimpse of God's redemptive work
in the midst of her suffering.
I wanna point this out.
Oftentimes in American Christianity,
we're like,
well, yeah, you were suffering,
but look, God's blessing you now.
It's like, no,
like we can sit in our suffering in the past,
the goodness of God in our lives
doesn't have to make us pretend like the suffering isn't there.
We can continue to wrestle with the ways in which we've suffered
and yet continue to move towards God
as we receive his blessing.
Verse 14,
at mealtime is where it gets good.
Boaz said to her,
come over here,
have some bread and dip it in the wine and vinegar.
When she sat down with the harvesters,
he offered some of the roasted grains.
She ate all that she wanted
and had some left over.
Boaz triples down on his generosity,
including her in table fellowship,
which means everything in this culture.
He says,
you belong here as a part of my family.
You have a spot to sit at the table.
This is a huge deal in their culture
and it's a huge deal in our culture.
It's one thing to serve food at a soup kitchen.
It's entirely different altogether
to grab a bowl yourself
and sit down next to the person that you're serving.
Boaz is treating Ruth like a part of the family,
even though she has no family.
This is the kingdom of God.
The generosity of God
lived out through one faithful, obedient person.
Is Boaz perfect?
Absolutely not.
But he is faithfully obeying the heart of God,
the widow, the orphan, and the foreigner.
Ruth, who is likely running on fumes
from a 50-mile journey with no food,
now has a hot meal prepared for her.
And that's no small thing.
Like she's gleaning, that's great,
but that seed is gonna have to be harvested.
It's gonna take a while for a real meal
to come out of the thing that she's gleaning.
And so Boaz gives her a warm meal.
It says she ate all that she could eat
and had some left over.
Remember I talked about the Bible
being one grand narrative?
All of the books of the Bible together
are telling one story.
Can you think of a time
where you've heard that phrase being used?
Ate all they could eat and had some left over?
Loaves and fish, right?
Same phrase.
Two miracles in the book of Matthew.
Feeding of the 5,000, the feeding of the 4,000.
The feeding of the 5,000
is a predominantly Jewish group of people.
They eat all they can eat
and have some left over.
How many baskets of food they have left over?
Anybody remember?
12.
We got 5,000 predominantly Jewish people.
They have 12 baskets left over.
12 as a representative of all the nation of Israel.
Jesus is saying with his miracle,
there is more than enough physical
and spiritual provision for the nation of Israel.
He doubles down two chapters later
and feeds a group of 4,000 people,
which were predominantly Gentile people.
They ate all they wanted
and had seven baskets left over.
Seven is the number that represents all of creation.
Jesus is saying in Ruth here and in Matthew there,
there is more than enough physical
and spiritual provision for Jews and for Gentiles.
Everything is God's.
And God cares for all of creation
and there is more than enough to go around.
And the more people that acknowledge that reality
and live into it,
the less widows, orphans, and foreigners will go hungry.
Or you could say it like this,
the more that God's people embody God's presence
through sacrificial love,
the more clearly we will see heaven come to earth.
And many of us opt out of this
because we don't have as much as Boaz.
We play the comparison game.
We say, well, he's rich, he's wealthy,
he's got social status.
But what we don't see is that Ruth
is being that same blessing to Naomi
even though she has nothing in her.
We can embody the kingdom of God
whether we're a widow with nothing in our hands
or a business owner with a lot in our hands.
God has not called us to worry about what's in our hands.
He's called us to trust him with what's in our hands
and steward it to those around us
in a way that embodies the kingdom of God
on earth as it is in heaven.
This story is gonna climax in a love story
between Ruth and Boaz,
but the underlying theme of the whole book
is a love story between God and his people
and the redemption that he can bring
if we would love him with our whole being
and love our neighbors as ourselves.
We gotta get going.
15 and 16.
As she got up to glean,
Boaz gave orders to his men,
let her gather among the sheaves
and don't reprimand her,
even pull out some of the stocks for her
from among the bundles
and leave them for her to pick up
and do not rebuke her.
So Ruth gleaned in the field until evening.
Then she threshed the barley
she had gathered
and then it amounted to about an ephah.
Boaz triples down on his generosity,
ensuring that Ruth will be treated well
and that her and Naomi will be provided for
above and beyond what a gleaner could ever imagine.
This is grace.
Grace is God treating us like we don't deserve
and could never pay back.
This is Boaz demonstrating the grace of God
to Ruth and Naomi,
giving them far more than they could ever work for,
far more than they could ever pay him back for.
Just as we see Ruth is a real person
who functions as a literary device
representing the most vulnerable among us,
Boaz is a literary foreshadowing of Christ
who will provide not just physical redemption
but spiritual redemption
to all who will cling to him in faith.
The story of Ruth is the story of the whole Bible
told in four chapters and three characters.
Ruth returns home
to what I would assume is a very anxious,
stressed out Naomi
because she knows how dangerous
gleaning in the fields can be,
especially as a foreigner.
She can't imagine what could have happened to Ruth.
So Ruth gleans and heads home.
She carries back a tremendous amount of grain
back to her mother-in-law.
Let's see here.
Ruth also brought,
where are we at?
Verse 18.
She carried it back to town
and her mother-in-law saw
how much she had gathered.
Ruth also brought out
and gave her what she had left over
from the lunch that she had eaten.
Her mother-in-law asked her,
where did you glean today
and where did you work?
Blessed is the man
who took notice on you.
Ifa is what most scholars would argue
about a half-month wages
of a legitimate worker in the field.
So now you've got a gleaner who,
and imagine how Boaz's workers
would have felt
as they see Ruth packing up
her two-weeks paycheck
from one day of work.
This is the kingdom of God.
It's not up to us
the way that God stewards
what he has given others.
So Ruth heads home
with about a half-month wages
and a warm meal.
Again, think about how impactful
this would be for Naomi.
She doesn't have to wait
a couple,
she doesn't have to wait
a long period of time
for them to get the grain
and harvest it
and roast it
and make a meal.
She has a warm meal
waiting for her,
something Naomi
would be desperate for.
Naomi is thrilled
to hear about this chance encounter,
which is probably how Naomi
is still viewing it
because she's bitter,
she's angry at God.
Call me Mara
for the Lord
has dealt bitterly with me.
This is a chance encounter
with a close relative
who could potentially play
another key role
in their redemption.
More on that next week.
She proclaims a blessing
over Boaz.
Blessed is the man
who took notice of you.
She says,
the Lord bless him.
He has not stopped
showing his kindness
to the living and the dead.
Naomi proclaims this blessing
over Boaz
and what she does
in this blessing
is she pinpoints the thing
that is motivating
all of Boaz's action.
In the blessing,
she says,
I might need to upgrade
my glasses, y'all.
The Lord bless him.
He has not stopped
showing loving kindness
to the living and the dead.
This Hebrew word
for loving kindness
is the word,
I'm going to say it
very American,
chesed.
There's a silent K
and it sounds like
you should be choking
when you say it.
If you say it properly,
I'm not going to try it.
I tried it earlier,
I embarrassed myself,
so we're going with chesed.
Chesed is the word
that represents
the character of God
most clearly
in the Old Testament.
It's promise-keeping loyalty
motivated by deep
personal care.
When God explains
his character
to the people of Israel
in Exodus,
he says,
the Lord is compassionate
and gracious,
slow to anger
and abounding in chesed,
steadfast love.
And what Naomi
recognizes here
is that Boaz's,
the motivation behind
Boaz's decisions
to help out Ruth
and Naomi
is far more
than attraction
to Ruth,
but it's the character
of God
lived out.
It's him having
a true,
genuine relationship
with Yahweh
and having the character
of God
so transform his life
that he can now
extend that character
to others.
The kingdom of God
is all about
seeing,
receiving,
and extending
the steadfast love.
It's not about
obeying laws
or following rules.
It's not about
doing the least amount
you can do
to help those in need.
It's about seeing
and experiencing
the compassionate,
faithful love of God.
It's about having
a radical encounter
with the God
who gave up everything
so that we could
have a relationship
with him.
And it's about
allowing that love
to transform us
from the inside out.
And that character
becoming a very part
of our own character,
being sanctified
into the image
of Jesus day
by day.
The kingdom of God
is about seeing,
receiving,
and extending
the loyal love
of God.
Naomi,
or Mara,
who is bitter
because of the way
God is treating her
is now able
to see God's character
visibly demonstrated
through Boaz.
Mara,
she might not be able
to see God
being faithful
just yet,
but she can see
Boaz,
a testimony
of God's faithfulness
right in front of her.
And I don't know
about you,
but I know
there are people
in my life
who are never
gonna step foot
into a church
just yet,
who've got baggage
in their past,
who are angry
with God,
who think things
are true about God
that are not true
of God,
and they might not
ever get to hear
a sermon preached
over them,
but they're gonna
interact with you
tomorrow at work.
And what Boaz
begins to do
for Naomi
is he begins
to model
the character
of God
for her
in tangible ways.
He says,
you think God's
been bitter to you,
but what I'm showing
is that God
has been extremely
gracious,
that he is
compassionate
and gracious,
that he's abounding
in steadfast love
to you.
you might be
the only Bible
somebody reads
tomorrow
or the next
day
day.
This is the beauty
of a biographical
testimony.
My hope is that
we can begin
to see our own
story with fresh
eyes
and begin
to imagine
how God
might use us
to impact
the lives
of others.
In this testimony,
we can see
God's loyal love
and redemption
being worked out
through the lives
of individuals
who are obedient
to him.
The book
clearly shows us
that even in the
midst of our own
suffering,
God is at work
bringing about
redemption.
It's a reminder
that God is
abundantly gracious
to us
even when we
don't deserve it
and can do
nothing to earn it.
And it invites us
to be extraordinarily
gracious to others
because of the grace
that he has shown us.
In the book of Ruth,
we see that we
aren't just the
beneficiaries of
God's loyal love,
but we are invited
to be benefactors
of God's loyal love
as well,
no matter our
circumstances.
Again, I love
the juxtaposition
between Ruth
and Boaz.
Boaz is a man
of wealth
with tremendous
social status.
And Ruth is a woman
with absolutely
no material possessions
to give,
no social status
to leverage,
and yet they both
demonstrate the
covenant love
of God
to those around them.
Later in chapter 3,
we're gonna see
that word
that was used
to describe Boaz
as being a man
of wealth
and social status.
It's gonna be used
to describe
Ruth's actions
towards Naomi.
It's about character.
It's about a heart
transformed by God.
She's got nothing,
and yet God uses her
to continue
Naomi's redemption story.
God can use you
to bring about redemption
into the lives
of those around you,
bringing God's kingdom
to earth
doesn't require us
to have full hands
but to have submitted hearts.
2 Chronicles 16, 9,
the eyes of the Lord
search the whole earth
in order to strengthen
those whose hearts
are fully committed
to him.
You wanna be a part
of cultivating
God's kingdom
on earth
as it is in heaven?
Surrender your heart
fully to him.
And I think
he'll blow you away
with what he can do
with it.
This chapter reminds us
that our everyday
ordinary lives
are charged
with redemptive potential
if only we have eyes
to see.
Boaz thought
he was waking up
to the daily grind
of the nine to five,
but God had different plans.
Ruth thought
she was just trying
to survive one more day,
but God had different plans.
How might this testimony
invite us to see
and participate
in his redemptive work
in our everyday lives?
Whether we're
a wealthy business owner,
a first grade teacher,
a physical therapist,
a government contractor,
or a stay-at-home mom,
how might God
use your daily life,
surrendered to him,
submitted to him,
to bring about
his redemptive work
in your life
and in the life
of those around you?
Like I said
at the start
of our time together,
I don't imagine
you'll remember
much of what I said
past Monday morning,
but I truly believe
that if you get
the story of Ruth
and the story
of the whole Bible
into your heart
and into your imagination,
it has the power
to change everything
that you do
from now until eternity.
Let's pray.